As you might imagine, I'm absolutely passionate
ربما كما تخيلتم، انا عاطفي جدا
about dance. I'm passionate about making it,
تجاه الرقص. أنا متحمس لصناعة الرقص،
about watching it, about encouraging others
ومشاهدته، و تشجيع الاخرين
to participate in it,
للمشاركة فيه،
and I'm also really passionate about creativity.
وأنا متحمس أيضا للإبداع.
Creativity for me is something that's absolutely critical,
الإبداع بالنسبة لي هو شيء مهم
and I think it's something that you can teach.
وأنا أعتقد أيضا أنه شيء يمكنك تدريسه.
I think the technicities of creativity can be taught
أنا أعتقد أن تقنية الإبداع بالإمكان تدريسها
and shared, and I think you can find out things
ومشاركتها، وأنا أيضا اعتقد أنه يمكنك إيجاد أشياء
about your own personal physical signature,
عن توقيعك الحقيقي الخاص بك،
your own cognitive habits, and use that as
عن عاداتك المقربة لك، واستخدامات التي هي
a point of departure to misbehave beautifully.
كنقطة رحيل لإساءة التصرف بشكل جميل.
I was born in the 1970s, and John Travolta was big
أنا ولدت في السبعينات، جون ترافولتا كان مشهورا
in those days: "Grease," "Saturday Night Fever,"
في تلك الأيام: "Grease" "Saturday Night Fever",
and he provided a fantastic kind of male role model for me
وقد قدم نموذج رائع بالنسبة لي
to start dancing. My parents were very up for me going.
لأبدأ الرقص. والداي كانا متحمسين جدا من أجلي للمتابعة.
They absolutely encouraged me to take risks, to go,
لقد دعموني كليا لاتخاذ الأخطار، لأواصل،
to try, to try. I had an opportunity, an access
لأجرب، لأجرب. لقد حصلت على فرصة الدخول
to a local dance studio, and I had an enlightened teacher
لقاعة الرقص المحلية، وكان لدي معلمة مثقفة
who allowed me to make up my own and invent
هي التي سمحت لي بصناعة واختراع
my own dances, so what she did was let me make up
رقصتي الخاصة، الذي فعلته هو أنها سمحت لي بصناعة
my own ballroom and Latin American dances to teach
قاعة الرقص الخاصة بي لتعليم الرقصات اللاتينية
to my peers.
لزملائي
And that was the very first time that I found an opportunity
وهذه كانت أول مرة حصلت فيها على فرصة
to feel that I was able to express my own voice,
للشعور بأني قادر على التعبير عن صوتي الخاص.
and that's what's fueled me, then, to become a choreographer.
وهذا هو الذي قام بتغذيتي لأصبح بعدها مصمماً للرقص.
I feel like I've got something to say and something to share.
أنا أشعر أنه لدي شيء لأقوله وشيء لأشاركه.
And I guess what's interesting is, is that I am now obsessed
واعتقد أن الشيء المثير للإنتباه هو أني الآن مهووس
with the technology of the body.
بتكنولوجيا الجسم.
I think it's the most technologically literate thing that we have,
أنا آعتقد انه آعظم شيئ مثقف تكنلوجياً لدينا،
and I'm absolutely obsessed with finding a way
وأنا أيضا مهووس جدا لإيجاد طريقة
of communicating ideas through the body to audiences
لتوصيل الأفكار للجمهور عن طريق الجسم
that might move them, touch them,
التي ربما تحركهم، تلمسهم،
help them think differently about things.
تساعدهم للتفكير بشكل مختلف عن الأشياء.
So for me, choreography is very much a process
إذا بالنسبة لي، تصميم الرقص هو قريب جدا لعملية
of physical thinking. It's very much in mind,
التفكير المادي، هو داخل العقل بشكل كبير جدا.
as well as in body, and it's a collaborative process.
كما هو في الجسم ايضا، وهو عملية تعاونية.
It's something that I have to do with other people.
هو شيء يجب علي القيام به مع الأشخاص الأخرين.
You know, it's a distributed cognitive process in a way.
كما تعلم. انها بطريقة ما عملية المعرفة الموزعة
I work often with designers and visual artists,
أنا اعمل غالبا مع مصممين وفنانين،
obviously dancers and other choreographers,
من المؤكد راقصين ومصممين للرقص.
but also, more and more, with economists,
لكن أيضا، زيادة على ذلك، مع خبراء إقتصاد،
anthropologists, neuroscientists, cognitive scientists,
علماء الأنثروبولوجياء، علماء الاعصاب و علماء المعرفة،
people really who come from very different domains of
أناس حقا جاءوا من مجالات مختلفة
expertise, where they bring their intelligence to bear
من الخبرة، يجلبون ذكائهم لضغطه لتحمل
on a different kind of creative process.
نوع مختلف من العمل الإبداعي.
What I thought we would do today a little bit is
الذي اعتقد اننا سنقوم بعمله هذه الليلة هو قليلا
explore this idea of physical thinking,
اكتشاف هذه الفكرة من التفكير الجسدي
and we're all experts in physical thinking.
ونحن جميعا خبراء في التفكير الجسدي.
Yeah, you all have a body, right?
نعم، جميعكم لديكم اجسام، هل هذا صحيح؟
And we all know what that body is like in the real world,
ونحن جميعا نعلم ماهية هذا الجسم في العالم الحقيقي،
so one of the aspects of physical thinking
إذا، أحد الجوانب في التفكير الجسدي.
that we think about a lot is this notion of proprioception,
هو أننا نفكر كثيراً عن فكرة استقبال الحس العميق
the sense of my own body in the space in the real world.
الإحساس لجسمي في فضاء في العالم الحقيقي.
So, we all understand what it feels like to know
إذا، نحن جميعا نعلم ماهو الشعور عندما تعلم
where the ends of your fingers are
أين هي نهاية امتداد اصابعك
when you hold out your arms, yeah?
عندما تمد ذراعيك، نعم؟
You absolutely know that when you're going to grab a cup,
آنت تعلم كليا عندما تريد الإمساك بكأس
or that cup moves and you have to renavigate it.
أو قد يتحرك الكأس فيجب عليك أن تعيد تحديد موقعه.
So we're experts in physical thinking already.
إذا نحن مسبقا خبراء بالتفكير الجسدي.
We just don't think about our bodies very much.
نحن فقط لا نفكر بأجسامنا كثيرا.
We only think about them when they go wrong, so, when
نحن فقط نفكر بأجسامنا عندما يحصل بها خلل، إذا، عندما
there's a broken arm, or when you have a heart attack,
يكون هناك ذراع مكسورة، أو عندما يكون لديك نوبة قلبية،
then you become really very aware of your bodies.
عندها تصبح حقا مدركا لجسمك
But how is it that we can start to think about using
لكن كيف يمكننا ان نبدأ التفكير في استخدام
choreographic thinking, kinesthetic intelligence, to arm
تفكير تصميم الرقص، الذكاء الحركي، من أجل تسليح
the ways in which we think about things more generally?
الطرق التى نفكر بها بالأشياء بشكل أعم؟
What I thought I'd do is, I'd make a TED premiere.
الذي فكرت في فعله هو عمل عرض اول ل TED.
I'm not sure if this is going to be good or not.
أنا لست متأكدا أن هذا سيكون جيدا او لا.
I'll just be doing it.
أنا فقط سأقوم به.
I thought what I'd do is, I'd use three versions
الذي فكرت في عمله هو استخدام ثلاث إصدارات
of physical thinking to make something.
من التفكير الجسدي لصناعة شيء.
I want to introduce you. This is Paolo. This is Catarina.
أرغب في التقديم لكم. هذا باولو وهذه كاترينا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
They have no idea what we're going to do.
ليس لديهما فكرة عن الذي سنقوم بعمله.
So this is not the type of choreography where
إذا هذا ليس النوع من تصميم الرقص عندما
I already have in mind what I'm going to make,
يكون لدي فكرة عن الذي سأقوم بعمله،
where I've fixed the routine in my head
عندما أقوم بتحديد الروتين في ذهني
and I'm just going to teach it to them,
وأقوم فقط بتعليمها لهم،
and these so-called empty vessels are just going to learn it.
وهؤلاء مايسمون بالأوعية الفارغة، سيتعلمونها فقط.
That's not the methodology at all that we work with.
هذه ليست المنهجية التي سنعمل عليها مطلقا.
But what's important about it is how it is that they're
لكن المهم كيف انهم
grasping information, how they're taking information,
يستوعبون المعلومات، كيف يحصلون عليها،
how they're using it, and how they're thinking with it.
كيف يستخدمونها، وكيف يفكرون معها.
I'm going to start really, really simply.
سأقوم بالبدء حقا، حقا ببساطة.
Usually, dance has a stimulus or stimuli, and I thought
عادة، الرقص لديه حافز أو حوافز، وأنا فكرت
I'd take something simple, TED logo, we can all see it,
بأخذ شيء بسيط، شعار TED ، نستطيع جميعا رؤيته،
it's quite easy to work with, and I'm going to do something
أنه بسيط جدا للعمل معه، وسأقوم بعمل شيء بسيط جدا،
very simply, where you take one idea from a body,
عندما تأخذ فكرة من جسم،
and it happens to be my body, and translate that
وصادف أنه جسمي، وتقوم بنقل هذا االشيء
into somebody else's body,
لجسم شخص آخر،
so it's a direct transfer, transformation of energy.
أذا هو نقل مباشر، تحويل للطاقة.
And I'm going to imagine this, you can do this too if you like,
وسأقوم بالتخيل، يمكنكم فعل هذا أيضا أذا أحببتم،
that I'm going to just take the letter "T" and I'm going
سأقوم فقط بأخذ الحرف "تي" وسأقوم
to imagine it in mind, and I'm going to place that outside in
بتخيله في ذهني، وسأقوم بوضعه خارجا
the real world. So I absolutely see a letter "T" in front of me.
في العالم الحقيقي، إذا أنا ارى الحرف "تي" أمامي.
Yeah? It's absolutely there.
نعم؟ إنه حقا هناك.
I can absolutely walk around it when I see it, yeah?
أنا حقا أستطيع المشي حوله عندما أراه، نعم؟
It has a kind of a grammar. I know what I'm going to do
لديه نوع من القاعدة. أنا أعلم ما سأقوم بعمله،
with it, and I can start to describe it, so I can describe it
وأنا أستطيع ان ابدأ بوصفه
very simply. I can describe it in my arms, right?
ببساطة. أستطيع وصفه بذراعي، صحيح؟
So all I did was take my hand and then I move my hand.
إذا، كل الذي فعلته هو أني رفعت يدي ثم حركتها.
I can describe it, whoa, in my head, you know? Whoa.
أستطيع وصفه، في ذهني، هل تعلمون؟
Okay. I can do also my shoulder. Yeah?
حسنا. أنا أستطيع تحريك كتفي أيضا. صحيح؟
It gives me something to do, something to work towards.
هي تعطيني شيئا لأفعله، شيئا لأعمل نحوه.
If I were to take that letter "T" and flatten it down
لو استطعت أن آخذ الحرف "تي" وأضعه
on the floor, here, maybe just off the floor,
على الأرض، هنا، ربما فقط فوق الأرض،
all of a sudden I could do maybe something with my knee,
فجأة يمكنني ان افعل شيئاً بركبتي ربما،
yeah? Whoa. So If I put the knee and the arms together,
صحيح؟ لو قمت بوضع ركبتي وذراعي معا،
I've got something physical, yeah? And I can start to build something.
لقد حصلت على شيء جسدي، صحيح؟ وأستطيع ان ابدأ ببناء شيء.
So what I'm going to do just for one and a half minutes or so
إذا الذي سأقوم بعلمه فقط لمدة دقيقة ونصف أو نحوها
is I'm going to take that concept, I'm going to make something,
هو أنني سأقوم بأخذ هذا المبدأ، وأقوم بصنع شيء،
and the dancers behind me are going to interpret it,
والراقصين خلفي سيقومون بترجمته،
they're going to snapshot it, they're going to take
والتقاطه، وسيأخذون نواحي منه،
aspects of it, and it's almost like I'm offloading memory
كأني أقوم بعلمية تفريغ للذاكرة
and they're holding onto memory? Yeah?
و هم يحتفظون بالذاكرة
And we'll see what we come up with.
وسوف نرى ما سنتوصل إليه.
So just have a little watch about how they're, how they're
أذا، فقط شاهدوا كيف يقومون
accessing this and what they're doing,
بالوصول لهذا وما الذي يفعلونه،
and I'm just going to take this letter "T," the letter "E,"
وأنا سأقوم بأخذ الحرف "تي"، والحرف "إي"
and the letter "D," to make something. Okay. Here goes.
والحرف" دي"، لصنع شيء. حسنا. سنبدأ.
So I have to get myself in the zone. Right.
إذا يجب علي بالدخول في المنطقة. حسنا.
It's a bit of a cross of my arm.
إنها تقريبا متقاطعة مع يدي
So all I'm doing is exploring this space of "T"
كل الذي أقوم بفعله الآن هو اكتشاف الحرف "تي"
and flashing through it with some action.
وأنطلق من خلالها لصنع حركات معينة.
I'm not remembering what I'm doing.
أنا لا اتذكر الذي افعله.
I'm just working on my task. My task is this "T."
أنا فقط أركز على مهمتي. مهمتي هي الحرف "تي"
Going to watch it from the side, whoa.
سأقوم بمشاهدته من الجهة الجانبية،
Strike moment.
لحظة الاكتشاف
That's it.
انتهينا.
So we're starting to build a phrase.
إذا نحن بدأنا بصناعة شكل.
So what they're doing, let's see, something like that,
إذا الذي يفعلونه، لنرى، شيء يشبه هذا،
so what they're doing is grasping aspects of that movement
إذا الذي يقومون بصنعه هو التقاط جوانب من الحركات
and they're generating it into a phrase.
ويقومون بتحويلها إلى عبارة.
You can see the speed is extremely quick, yeah?
لاحظو أن االسرعة عالية جدا، صحيح؟
I'm not asking them to copy exactly.
أنا لا أطالبهم بتقليدي تماما.
They're using the information that they receive
إنهم يستخدمون المعلومات التي يستقبلونها.
to generate the beginnings of a phrase.
لصناعة بداية العبارة.
I can watch that and that can tell me something
أستطيع مشاهدتهم، وهذا سوف يوضح لي
about how it is that they're moving.
كيف يتحركون.
Yeah, they're super quick, right?
نعم، إنهم بالغوا السرعة، صحيح؟
So I've taken this aspect of TED and translated it
أذا أن قمت بأخذ هذا الجانب من "تيد" وترجمته
into something that's physical.
إلي شيء جسماني.
Some dancers, when they're watching action,
بعض الراقصين عندما يشاهدون حركات
take the overall shape, the arc of the movement,
يأخذون الشكل العام، للرقصة،
the kinetic sense of the movement,
الاحساس الحركي الذي في الرقصة،
and use that for memory.
ويستخدمونها للذاكرة.
Some work very much in specific detail.
بعضهم ينجح في بالتفاصيل الدقيقة.
They start with small little units and build it up.
هم يبدوأون بجزء بسيط ثم يبنون الباقي.
Okay, you've got something? One more thing.
حسنا، هل فهمتم ماأعنيه؟ بقي معلومة أخرى.
So they're solving this problem for me,
إذا هم يقومون بحل هذه المشكلة لي،
having a little --
يحصلون على القليل
They're constructing that phrase.
ثم يبنون تلك العبارة
They have something and they're going to hold on to it,
لقد حصلوا على شيء وسوف يقومون بالتمسك به.
yeah? One way of making.
صحيح؟ طريقة واحدة
That's going to be my beginning in this world premiere.
هذا سيكون البداية في هذا العرض العالمي الأول.
Okay. From there I'm going to do a very different thing.
حسناً. من تلك النقطة سأقوم بعمل شيئ مختلف تماماً
So basically I'm going to make a duet.
سأقوم بعمل رقصة ثنائية في الاساس
I want you to think about them as architectural objects,
اريدك ان تفكر بهم كأغراض معمارية
so what they are, are just pure lines.
اذا هم عبارة عن خطوط نقية فقط.
They're no longer people, just pure lines, and I'm going
أنهم لم يعودوا اناس، خطوط نقية فقط، وأنا ذاهب
to work with them almost as objects to think with, yeah?
للعمل معهم تقريبا كأشياء نفكر بها، نعم؟
So what I'm thinking about is taking
ما أفكر به هو أخذ
a few physical extensions from the body as I move, and
بعض الامتدادات الجسدية من الجسم وأنا اتنقل، و
I move them, and I do that by suggesting things to them:
أنقلها، وافعل ذلك بإقتراح الأشياء لهم.
If, then; if, then. Okay, so here we go.
إذا، بعد ذلك؛..إذا، بعد ذلك. حسنا، هيا نبدأ.
Just grab this arm.
فقط امسك هذه الذراع.
Can you place that down into the floor?
هل يمكنك أن تضع ذلك الى للاسفل علي الارض
Yeah, down to the floor. Can you go underneath?
نعم، وصولاً إلى الارض. هل يمكن أن تذهب تحتها؟
Yeah. Cat, can you put leg over that side? Yeah.
نعم. هل يمكنك وضع الساق على هذا الجانب؟ نعم.
Can you rotate?
هل يمكنك التدوير؟
Whoom, just go back to the beginning.
وووم، ارجعوا إلى البداية.
Here we go, ready? And ... bam, bake ... (clicks metronome)
وهيا نبدأ، جاهزة؟ و.. بام... باك...
Great. Okay, from there, you're both getting up.
جيد. حسنا، من هناك، انتما الاثنان تنهضان لأعلى.
You're both getting up. Here we go. Good, now? Them.
انتم الاثنان تنهضان. جيد، الآن؟ لهم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So from there, from there, we're both getting up,
لذا من هناك، ومن هناك، نحن الاثنان نقوم
we're both getting up, going in this direction,
أننا نحن الاثنان ننهض و نسير في هذا الاتجاه،
going underneath. Whoa, whoa, underneath.
الذهاب تحت.، أسفل.
Whoa, underneath, whoo-um. Yeah? Underneath. Jump.
قف، تحت، أم. نعم؟ تحت. اقفز.
Underneath. Jump. Paolo, kick. Don't care where. Kick.
تحت. الانتقال السريع. باولو، اركل. لا تهتم اين.
Kick, replace, change a leg. Kick, replace, change the leg.
ركلة, استبدال, تغيير ساق. ركلة، استبدال، غير الساق.
Yeah? Okay? Cat, almost get his head. Almost get his head.
نعم؟ حسنا؟ تقريبا احصل على رأسه. تقريبا احصل على رأسه.
Whoaa. Just after it, maybe. Whoaa, whaaay, ooh.
وا. فقط بعد ذلك، ربما. وا، وااي، أوه.
Grab her waist, come up back into her first, whoom, spin,
امسك بخصرها، ارجع لها اولاً، وووم، تدور،
turn her, whoo-aa. (Snaps) Great.
فم بتدويرها . (فرطقة) جيد
Okay, let's have a little go from the beginning of that.
حسنا، لقد دعونا نرجع الى بداية تلك.
Just, let me slow down here. Fancy having eight -- (Laughter)
فقط، اسمحوا لي أن ابطئ هنا. رائع ان كانت ثمانية(ضحك)
Fancy having eight hours with me in a day.
ثماني ساعات معي في يوم واحد.
So, maybe too much. So, here we go, ready, and -- (Clicks metronome)
لذا، ربما أكثر من اللازم. وهكذا، وهنا نذهب، جاهزون، و--(نقرات)
(Clicks metronome)
(نقرات)
Nice, good job. Yeah? Okay. (Applause)
حسناً، عمل جيد. نعم؟ حسنا. (تصفيق)
Okay, not bad. (Applause) A little bit more?
حسنا، ليس سيئاً. (تصفيق) أكثر قليلاً؟
Yeah. Just a little bit more, here we go, from that place.
نعم. أكثر بقليل، ومن هنا نذهب، من ذلك المكان.
Separate. Face the front. Separate. Face the front.
انفصلوا. اتجهوا الى المقدمة. انفصلوا. اتجهوا الى المقدمة.
Imagine that there's a circle in front of you, yeah?
تخيلوا أن هناك دائرة أمامك، نعم؟
Avoid it. Avoid it. Whoom. Kick it out of the way.
تجنب ذلك. تجنب ذلك. وووم. اركله ليبعد عن الطريق.
Kick it out of the way. Throw it into the audience. Whoom.
اركله ليبعد من الطريق. ارميها في الحضور. وووم.
Throw it into the audience again.
ارميها إلى الجمهور مرة أخرى.
We've got mental architecture, we're sharing it,
لقد حصلنا على البنية العقلية، و نحن نتشاركها،
therefore solving a problem. They're enacting it.
و بهذا يحلون مشكلة. هم يشرعونها.
Let me just see that a little bit. Ready, and go.
واسمحوا لي فقط أن ارى ذلك قليلاً. جاهزين؟، وابدءوا.
(Clicks metronome)
(نقرات)
Okay, brilliant. Okay, here we go. From the beginning,
حسنا، رائع. حسنا. ومنذ البداية،
can we do our phrases first? And then that.
هل يمكننا أن نفعل العبارات أولاً؟ وثم أن.
And we're going to build something now, organize it,
ونحن في طريقنا لبناء شيء الآن، وتنظيمها،
the phrases. Here we go. Nice and slow?
العبارات. هنا نذهب. بلطف و ببطء؟
Ready and go ... um. (Clicks metronome)
جاهزون؟ وابدءوا.. أم. (نقرات)
(Clicks metronome)
(نقرات)
The duet starts. (Clicks metronome)
يبدأ للرقصة الثنائية. (نقرات)
So yeah, okay, good. Okay, nice, very nice. (Applause)
لذا نعم، حسنا، جيد. حسنا، رائع، رائع جداً. (تصفيق)
So good. So -- (Applause)
جيد جدًا. ذلك-(تصفيق)
Okay. So that was -- (Applause)
حسنا. اذن ذلك كان--(تصفيق)
Well done. (Applause)
أحسنت. (تصفيق)
That was the second way of working.
هذه هي الطريقة الثانية للعمل.
The first one, body-to-body transfer, yeah,
الأولى، النقل من جسم إلى جسم، نعم،
with an outside mental architecture that I work with
مع بنية عقلية خارجية وأنا أعمل مع
that they hold memory with for me.
أن لديهم الذاكرة بالنسبة لي.
The second one, which is using them as objects to think
الثانية، وهي استخدامهم كأشياء للتفكير
with their architectural objects, I do a series of
بأغراضهم المعمارية ، اقوم بسلسلة من
provocations, I say, "If this happens, then that.
الحث، وأقول، "إذا حدث هذا ، ثم ذلك
If this, if that happens -- " I've got lots of methods like that,
إذا حدث هذا، إذا حدث ذلك "لقد حصلت على الكثير من أساليب مثل هذا،
but it's very, very quick, and this is a third method.
ولكنها سريعة جداً، وهذا أسلوب ثالث.
They're starting it already, and this is a task-based method,
أنهم بدأوا ذلك فعلا، وهذا أسلوب معتمد على المهام،
where they have the autonomy to make
حيث أنها تتمتع بتحكم ذاتي لعمل
all of the decisions for themselves.
جميع القرارات بأنفسهم.
So I'd like us just to do, we're going to do a little
ولذلك أود أن نفعل، نحن سنقوم بعمل القليل من
mental dance, a little, in this little one minute,
الرقص العقلي، قليلاً، في دقيقة واحدة ،
so what I'd love you to do is imagine,
وما اريدكم ان تقوموا به هو تخيل،
you can do this with your eyes closed, or open, and if you
يمكنك القيام بذلك مع عينيك مغلقة، أو مفتوحة، وإذا كنت
don't want to do it you can watch them, it's up to you.
لا تريد أن تفعل ذلك يمكنك مشاهدتهم، والأمر متروك لكم.
Just for a second, think about that word "TED" in front of
لثانية فقط فكر في أن كلمة "TED" أمامك
you, so it's in mind, and it's there right in front of your mind.
اذا هي في عقلك، و انها هناك أمام عقلك.
What I'd like you to do is transplant that outside
ما أود منك القيام به هو زرعها في الخارج
into the real world, so just imagine that word "TED"
في العالم الحقيقي، فقط تخيل أن كلمة "TED"
in the real world.
في العالم الحقيقي.
What I'd like you to do what that is take an aspect of it.
ما أود منك أن تقوم به هو ان تأخذ جانبا منه.
I'm going to zone in on the "E," and I'm going to
أنا سأركز ف "E"، وأنا سوف اقوم بتغيير
scale that "E" so it's absolutely massive,
حجم "E" حيث أنها ضخمة جداً
so I'm scaling that "E" so it's absolutely massive,
الان انا اغير حجم ال "E" حتى تصبح عملاقة
and then I'm going to give it dimensionality.
و عندها سأعطيها أبعاد.
I'm going to think about it in 3D space. So now,
أنا سأفكر بها كشكل ثلاثي الأبعاد. الآن،
instead of it just being a letter that's in front of me,
بدلاً من كونها مجرد حرف أمامي،
it's a space that my body can go inside of.
أنها مساحة التي يمكن لجسدي ان يذهب لداخلها.
I now decide where I'm going to be in that space,
الان اقرر اين انا ذاهب في ذلك الفضاء،
so I'm down on this small part of the bottom rib
أنا الان في أسفل الجزء صغير من الضلع السفلي
of the letter "E," and I'm thinking about it, and I'm imagining
للحرف "E"، وأنا أفكر حول هذا الموضوع، وأنا أتخيل
this space that's really high and above. If I asked you to
هذا الفضاء حقاً مرتفع وعالي. إذا طلبت منك أن
reach out — you don't have to literally do it, but in mind —
تمتد – ليس عليك فعل ذلك وحرفيا. لكن في العقل —
reach out to the top of the "E," where would you reach?
ابسط نفسك إلى الجزء العلوي من "E" اين ستصل؟
If you reach with your finger, where would it be?
إذا كان يمكنك الوصول إلىها بالإصبع، اين ستكون؟
If you reach with your elbow, where would it be?
إذا كنت تصل إلىها بالكوع الخاص بك، اين ستكون؟
If I already then said about that space that you're in,
إذا كنت انا بالفعل تكلمت حول ذلك الفضاء الذي كنت فيه،
let's infuse it with the color red, what does that do
دعونا نسرب لها اللون الأحمر، وماذا فعل ذلك
to the body? If I then said to you, what happens if
للجسم؟ إذا قلت لك حينها، ماذا يحدث إذا
that whole wall on the side of "E" collapses and you have to
انهار كل الجدارعلى جانب "E"، وعليك أن
use your weight to put it back up,
تستخدم الوزن الخاص بك لإرجاعها كما كانت
what would you be able to do with it?
ماذا كان بمقدورك ان تفعل بها؟
So this is a mental picture, I'm describing a mental,
اذن هذه صورة عقلية، انا اصف صورة
vivid picture that enables dancers to make choices
حية تمكن الراقصين من تحديد الخيارات
for themselves about what to make.
لأنفسهم حول ما يجب ان يعملوا.
Okay, you can open your eyes if you had them closed.
حسنا، يمكنك فتح عينيك إذا كانت مغلقة.
So the dancers have been working on them.
الراقصين كانوا يعملون عليها.
So just keep working on them for a little second.
واصل العمل بها لثانية قليلة.
So they've been working on those mental architectures in the here.
حيث كانوا يعملون في تلك المعمارية الذهنية هنا.
I know, I think we should keep them as a surprise.
أنا أعرف، وأعتقد أننا ينبغي الاحتفاظ بهم كمفاجأة.
So here goes, world premiere dance. Yeah? Here we go.
من هنا نذهب، عرض الرقص العالمي الاول. نعم؟ هيا نذهب.
TED dance. Okay. Here it comes. I'm going to organize it quickly.
رقصة TED. حسنا. سأقوم بتنظيم ذلك بسرعة.
So, you're going to do the first solo that we made,
هكذا، ستقوم بعمل الرقصة الفردية الاولى التي صممناها
yeah blah blah blah blah, we go into the duet, yeah,
نعم بلاه بلاه بلاه بلاه، نذهب إلى الرقصة الثنائية، نعم،
blah blah blah blah. The next solo, blah blah blah blah,
بلاه بلاه بلاه بلاه. الرقصة الفردية التالية، بلاه بلاه بلاه بلاه،
yeah, and both at the same time, you do the last solutions.
نعم، وكلاهما في نفس الوقت، يمكنك القيام باخر حل.
Okay? Okay. Ladies and gentlemen, world premiere,
حسنا؟ حسنا. أيها السيدات والسادة، العرض العالمي الاول،
TED dance, three versions of physical thinking. (Applause)
رقصة TED، ثلاثة إصدارات من التفكير الجسدي. (تصفيق)
Well, clap afterwards, let's see if it's any good, yeah? (Laughter)
حسنا، التصفيق بعد ذلك، دعونا نرى ما إذا كانت جيدة، نعم؟ (ضحك)
So yeah, let's clap -- yeah, let's clap afterwards.
نعم، دعونا نصفق-نعم، لنصفق بعد ذلك.
Here we go. Catarina, big moment, here we go, one.
هيا نذهب. كاتارينا، لحظة كبيرة، وهيا نذهب، واحد.
(Clicks metronome)
(نقرات)
Here it comes, Cat. (Clicks metronome)
وهنا يأتي (نقرات)
Paolo, go. (Clicks metronome) Last you solo.
باولو، ابدأ. (نقرات) و في الاخر قم برقصة فردية.
The one you made. (Clicks metronome)
الواحدة التي قمت بعملها. (نقرات)
(Clicks metronome)
(نقرات)
Well done. Okay, good. Super. So --
أحسنت. حسنا، جيد. سوبر.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So -- (Applause)
ذلك-(تصفيق)
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا. (تصفيق)
So -- three versions. (Applause) Oh. (Laughs)
لذا-ثلاثة إصدارات. (تصفيق) أوه. (ضحك)
(Applause) Three versions of physical thinking, yeah?
(تصفيق) ثلاثة إصدارات من التفكير الجسدي، نعم؟
Three versions of physical thinking. I'm hoping that today,
ثلاثة إصدارات من التفكير الجسدي. وأنا على أمل أن اليوم،
what you're going to do is go away and make a dance
ما كنت تنوي القيام به هو الذهاب و عمل رقصات
for yourself, and if not that,
لنفسك، وإذا لم يكن ذلك،
at least misbehave more beautifully, more often.
على الأقل اسئ التصرف بصورة أكثر جمالا، أحياناً اكثر
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكرا جزيلا. (تصفيق)
Thank you. Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا. شكرا. (تصفيق)
Here we go. (Applause)
هيا نذهب. (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)